welcome to the stoah the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now in
this session of a series called sensing
the new myth this is the third of the
series we are joined by Michael Mead
michael is a mythologist and author a
storyteller and he hosts podcasts called
living myth podcast among other series
that you'll be able to learn more about
at the end of this session and this has
been an essential part of my sense
making diet to have the mythic lens and
the storytelling perspective on what is
happening in the world right now the
meta crisis and the upheaval and me what
Michael might describe is the collective
initiation the humanity is going through
and so I feel very grateful that Michael
is here with us today this is special to
me I'm very meaningful and I'm just
excited to be here with you all
appreciate you all being here the
session will go on till the end of the
hour and then there will be a 30-minute
sense-making practice for anyone who
wishes to stay I will be facilitating so
if you want to stick around we'll do
some breakout rooms and a collective
dialogue to continue the conversation
amongst ourselves
so welcome Michael thanks for being here
good to be with you all right I'm gonna
start us off with why I have been so
enthusiastic about Michael being here at
the stoah and with all of us
working on so many different projects
and having different passions one of the
golden threads that I see between us all
is this return to community us a deeper
sense of community and in one of
Michael's recent podcasts he said we are
being called to awaken the soul of
humanity and reweave the
bonds of communities and that really
resonated with me and with what I think
it is that I'm doing here at the store
some of you and in our individual
projects as well and so my question what
I'm curious about Michael is how does
communitas support and how can what to
what extent is it necessary for the
discovery of and the expression of
personal genius or to what extent is
that discovery like a lone wolf hero's
journey and and then also relating that
to the idea that when enough of us
awaken to this a genius how that
supports the collective initiation so
I'm sort of wanting to tie these ideas
of personal genius communitas and
collective initiation together as
somewhat of a compass for me in my
pursuits of designing for communitas and
how to to do that with wisdom and
direction so that is um where my inquiry
is aiming and if that makes sense to you
I would love to hear you speak about
that okay thank you
so welcome everyone genius to me I've
redefined genius the common sense of
genius is high IQ or specific rare
talent but the word genius from the
Latin means the spirit that's already
there so it's the spirit that's there
inside each person born and the old idea
would be that that spirit that seed of
genius is in the soul so the idea is
each person comes in each person like
each tree in the forest is unique and
inside the soul of that unique person is
the spirit of genius trying waiting to
awaken and so I distinguish genius from
talent talent is a part of genius talent
is a an old German word for the weight
used to measure gold
so that tells me that if the person
doesn't express their talent it becomes
a weight on their soul and so talent is
part of it but not the whole of it
other capacities are involved and also
distinct ways of feeling erratically
connected to the world are part of the
genius kind of core but another thing
that I think is really important is each
genius has its own style so that if
you're interested in a certain kind of
music you'll soon start to select out oh
that's how so-and-so please that's how
so-and-so plays they can play the same
instrument but they play with their
style so style is not a fashion word
style goes back to the Latin word
stylist something that is engraved and
so a person's style is really something
engraved or you could say written on
their soul and awakening to that style
gives a person their entry points into
life so to me genius is presents and
everyone born and and as a result it's
more pertinent to me than heroics
so the hero's journey comes from the
early book by Joseph Campbell hero with
a thousand faces and in the book he
calls the hero's myth the monomyth the
only story and I really disagree I wrote
a book called the genius myths saying
that whereas the hero is tends to be
aggressive masculine muscular and aimed
at an out of thing
the genius is something already in
everybody regardless of its male or
female or any kind of gender orientation
any kind of ethnic background everyone
has it so that to me seems more
important and where it relates to the
meta crises as you called it
is so the way I look at that is the
biggest crisis in the world right now is
global climate change because it affects
all the ecosystems all the living beings
the waters and the entire earth and then
right below that now we have the corona
virus pandemic which so you have a an
ecological crisis and then below it we
have the pandemic which is like really a
humanitarian crisis that has to do with
health and now it has its own economic
crisis and but it's really at the
humanitarian level and then the third
major crisis right now I think was the
death of George Floyd being deprived of
the life life breath right in front of
everybody as a actual thing and as a
symbol of racial injustice but all kinds
of other oppressions in the world so
that the death of that one person spread
throughout the world and it's still
affecting people's passions and ideas
about injustice and so it's as if we're
in this cascade of crises and each one
of them is complex each has its own
history and each has a mystery in it in
a sense as well so my sense is heroic
activities have kind of gotten us in the
trouble we're in and the only way I see
getting out is that there's a greater
awakening of all the diverse unique
geniuses inside as many people as
possible because when a person awakens
to the Jew their genius they also get an
orientation into life in other words
some people are already carrying inside
you could say before birth some capacity
to work in nature to work with forests
the real rebuilding of forests while
someone else has more of a natural
capacity for hospice work and someone
else has a capacity to work on vaccines
and someone else has a capacity for
pediatrics and helping children and so
it's all of those things
operating at the same time at a more
awakened level that would give us the
capacity to take on all the complexities
of all the levels of crisis so that's
that's how I see that going together
um and then for me this idea of genius
latent genius is connected to the notion
of calling and so you know that the two
different roads you could say into the
world are career which is usually either
chosen by someone else or chosen unto
some more superficial level of decision
and then calling a vocation where it's
not us choosing we are chosen and to me
that's the deeper richer thing it used
to be called the second adventure of
life the first adventure as we say in
the modern world is get a life the
second adventure is respond to the call
and the call is calling to the genius
that's already there the call isn't
simply going out and finding the
treasure or the you know whatever it
might be that person is looking for the
knowledge the call is calling to the
genius that's already inside and the
genius already knows the nature of
itself and the nature of its work so
that there's the old idea with everybody
also has a library inside them with all
the knowledge that they're looking for
not that we don't have to go out into
the world because we have to be a person
of our times and we have to feel the
marketplace and the struggles of life
but at the same time there's knowledge
inside trying to awaken and so the old
way of helping young people into this
state of awakening which would be self
revelation on one hand and then also
some healing on the other hand and that
would be done through the process of
initiation or rites of passage which at
one time would have existed all around
the world and then I call that an
archetypal arrangement I also think that
the dynamic underneath transformation is
passage and I'll say something about
that shape in a minute but so what would
happen in theory is a young person girl
boy whomever it is would at a certain
age go into an artful ritual process
which would be aimed at several things
one awakening the soul with its genius
with its kind of natural inclinations
with its colleague and then on the other
hand repeating everyone gets wounded
some people deny it but most people are
wounded in childhood everybody
experiences abandonment and everybody
experiences some sense of wound and part
of the idea is if we got everything we
wanted through the family at home we
would never leave we'd all remain
children something is missing and
usually some wound has been given and
that drives people out into the world
but the the rite of passage would be the
kind of elaborate artful deep awakening
process between leaving childhood and
entering the world so that when a person
enter the world that no longer a child
there are more awakened version of
themselves and part of that would be
some healing of early life wounds so
that a person would learn about their
own wounds they would learn about the
process of healing and if they wound up
in a position of power they would have
compassion for others because they would
understand woundedness and they would
understand the need for healing
especially in times like this so I'm
calling the rites of passage the
underlying dynamic of transformation and
in classically there's three steps the
first step is separation the second one
is transition also called the liminal
period and the third one is a return to
community but at a new level of
understanding and acceptance by a
conscious community that would be a
successful rite of passage so what I'm
saying is literally we are now all
separated many people are in quarantine
or partial quarantine we are socially
distant
separated we're not able to have social
gatherings a lot of people have lost
their jobs there's been a breakdown of
all the institutional functional ways
that people socialize and and we're more
separate as a result yes we're on zoom'
all the time but that's only a partial
thing so we're literally in separation
and so my sense of things kind of mythic
story view is once something happens
like that the soul thinks we're in an
initiation the soul is this ancient and
immediate thing that has this these old
memories of human imagination and so I
think the soul thinks oh they're doing
an initiation again because they're all
separate then the second stage is called
transition so you're moving from one
form through a transition to another
form whether it's the individual all the
collective but I like the idea that that
in-between stage the betwixt them
between is liminal liminal comes from
the old Latin word lemon which is the
base of a doorway the threshold and so
that it means you go from one space onto
the threshold then into the next space
so we're in a threshold condition or a
liminal condition and and liminality
includes the breakdown of structures the
loss of patterns and and the opening up
at a very deep level level to unusual
opportunities but more immediately
opening up to uncertainty and the need
to face the unknown and so that that's
called liminal then you could say if
you're on the threshold or the lemon the
nearby word is subliminal which means
below the threshold someone something's
trying to come up so if you accept the
idea that we're in this uncertain
liminal betwixt them between condition
there's a suggestion that what we're
looking for is not the next strategic
plan to get us back into the world as it
was but actually something from the
unconscious or the unseen that's trying
to enter us and can only do so
when the institution's rattle and the
structures are loosened so on one hand
we're in terrible crises that have to be
faced on the other hand we're on the
threshold or the verge of finding the
next view of the world so in the middle
ground the way I imagined it on one hand
you have this liminality and uncertainty
and right next to it you have a greater
opportunity for community toss committee
toss being deep community something
happens that's so deep and so meaningful
it pulls people together without even
the opportunity to figure out what their
differences are the differences kind of
melt away because the deep soul becomes
so activated and there's lots of ways to
imagine that one way I saw it recently
is in watching the protests of black
lives matter and those few moments where
there's a conversation between the
police and the protesters and something
happens and they all kneel down and
that's communitas in the middle of all
the commotion with smoke burning in the
building behind them with everything
undecided and no one knows what's going
on they find a moment to kneel and come
to the ground together that's the deep
ground of community tasks so it can
happen in a moment and it happens in
unexpected and surprising ways and so my
understanding is from those two things
suffering through the liminality the
betwixt in between the uncertainty the
radical changes and finding moments of
deep humanity deep community tasks for
the individual but possibly for the
group as well that creates the energy
and opens the imagination to get the
ideas and the images for the next world
and so then you arrive at the end of the
big transition and everything and
everyone has changed and then you begin
the process over again that's the frame
I'm using to understand what we're in
and one other thing I should add if when
there's a rite of passage or you can
also call it initiation
which means initiate means to step in to
begin to begin again and again really
but there's always a brush with death
there's something that feels like life
and death and so that's because the
background idea and you could say the
mystery behind creation is life death
renewal in terms of a personal
initiation its birth death rebirth so
I'm using a very old idea that says this
whole thing with all its crises nature
the cosmos the individual psyche all
participating in life death renewal and
so part of the liminal space and the
middle ground is the death of things
like recently here in the United States
people decided to try and go back some
people to try and go back to normal as
they call it and it just didn't work it
created more abnormal
so once the rite of passage is underway
once the initiation is underway there's
no going back and the only thing is to
go forward and the other thing I would
just say maybe to bring it to a close is
initiation takes us further and deeper
into something than we would choose to
go on our own it has to have that
feeling of letting go I don't know
what's going on and a sense of
submission to the adventure and so I
think that has happened collectively to
everyone now we're way further into
things than we would have chosen to go
people would regulate it more we're
already in radical circumstances and so
I'm suggesting these old ideas are ways
to shape or hold some shape while
everything is trying to change
thank you that was wonderful please guys
drop your questions in the chat there
and then I will call on you to unmute
and ask your question I will ask one
question and then go to that one thing
we're doing here at the snow michael is
developing an ecology of practices and
experimenting with different life
practices and psycho technologies we can
engage in as a community to develop
sovereignty and resilience and
communitas and in this liminal space and
so I'm wondering of what comes up for
you as like essential life practices for
developing sovereignty and communitas
yeah that we might get that we might
experiment with or even repurpose for
the current moment so in mythological
terms there's two main roads of practice
and one is the contemplative road
nowadays in many Western cultures now
you have meditation Eastern style and
you have yoga which is also has a
contemplative component to it
so one road has always been
contemplation and meditation and you
find that amongst the original Greek
philosophers also they had their
practices of contemplation and then the
other road has always been expressive
arts so one is the turning in and
quieting down and removing from the
dynamics of life and the other is the
jumping in and the fully expressing into
the dynamics of life those are the two
roads and so part of the experiment is
to figure out which road a person most
likely goes on I'm on the expressive
side I have the Irish gift or curse of
gab and I'm gonna talk at length about
almost anything and tell stories and so
on like that
and and that's really a natural practice
that lines up with you know what's
inside me trying to come out but because
I write I go into a very contemplative
practice when I'm writing I don't see
anyone I just see words and work with
that and so my understanding is in the
course of life a person's gonna have to
learn a series of practices because the
psyche changes and what was maybe
primarily meditative suddenly now has to
get more expressive in order to find
balance and keep the psyche growing and
so at least that's a way to begin so one
more idea because if you follow the idea
of a core genius waiting to unfold then
there are going to be certain practices
that are natural to a person and and so
well there's lots of ways to get into
that but certain people will find the
inclination to music where if someone
will find the inclination to they want
to be in nature all the time well that
becomes a practice in the ancient world
that was a practice and so maybe that's
the starting way to think about it thank
you
rain will you ask a question yeah hi
Michael thanks for being here my
question is effectively about the
ontology of this genius in the I hear an
implicit individuality in it in a way
like that genius comes from the soul and
maybe I'm misunderstanding that but I'd
love to hear kind of how you how you see
individuality and is is this genius you
talk about an individual property or a
collective property or some negotiation
between the two thank you great question
so I see genius has probably the
uniqueness of a person so
one of the old ideas is the uniqueness
of the soul each person born is unique
from anyone else maybe similar people
but never that person and part of the
salvation of one's inner troubles is
learning to be with and express one's
uniqueness it's the essential for any
kind of expressive art but even I think
for a meaningful intellectual work so I
think it's something unique to the
person now the genius needs to be
received by the community or else it
backfires it backs up so the community
becomes the receiving part for the
genius of the individual people and then
the individual people's genius is the
ongoing inspiration and imagination of
the community so there's a relationship
between the two if you think of the
genius as gifted the talents as gifts
and other capacities as gifts to be
given so that you can imagine
a instead of a consumer society a
gift-giving society where everybody has
helped to give their gifts and the
community is the beneficiary of the
gifts but then there's an old idea that
when you give from the genius you don't
get less genius you get more that giving
from the genius intensifies and
elaborates the capacity of the genius I
mean that's one way that I think about
it and I should say in classic terms and
in mythology the genius is not human
it's a spirit and so there's a
negotiation between the host of the
genius and the genius
for instance I have friends who are
painters and you know they always want
to have the next big gallery show and
when they have the show they're painting
right up to the last minute you know
people are saying stop stop now I gotta
one more painting up there well that's
not the person that's the genius the
genius doesn't care about the body or
anything like that the genius just wants
expression so my understanding of the
genius it's a spirit that we have to
negotiate with and it's something that
transcends the personal and certainly
cannot be contained or defined by the
communal the genius is defiant against
restrictions
thank you Chris will you ask your
question hi Michael um I've been reading
Thomas Singer you and that union analyst
his characterization of cultural
complexes and I was struck about how he
says that cultural complexes get
momentum and we're in the middle of a
really strong cultural complex and he
says they don't stop until there's a
force greater than a complex what do you
think that force may be and it makes me
somewhat pessimistic because I think it
won't be a positive force would you're
not hey Chris good question thank you so
I love that idea of the collectives orc
complex so here's one way I'm seeing it
just to take an example the United
States is suffering under an exacerbated
complex of narcissism having elected
Donald Trump who is an arch narcissist
to a place of high power which is the
kind of thing no one should ever do
because the narcissist can't help but
turn everything to themselves and then
undermine themselves as well as anything
else everything else and so this has now
been mmm
someone with with really radical
narcissistic complications is now in the
seat of great power and so everything is
endangered and I've been suggesting that
there's another thing about narcissism
narcissistic people can put a spell on
other people people think that they're
being receiving attention from them
narcissus but the narcissus is really
putting them under what in stories would
be called a spell so that people begin
acting out the things that the
narcissistic person wants this happens
in families a lot so if you take that
configuration and you say what's the
force that could counteract that I would
say truth I would say truth that that
the the narcissistic complex distorts
reality and so what's needed is truth I
don't think it's a bad thing at all I
think it's an insane truth I'm thinking
of the old idea of satyagraha the force
of truth that's what Gandhi called it
when he walked a cloth across India to
pick up some salt and that was the
movement that broke the British Raj
really broke down because of the forth
of truth force of truth and he called it
satyagraha so it's not truth on a
scientific level per se and it's not
truth in an agreed-upon
understanding of culture it's a it's a
penetrating transcendent truth Gandhi
went against the law because the law was
you could not take salt the salt was
owned by the British East India Company
and any person who took salt was
violating the law well salt is a
necessity for life
and Gandhi understood that and he
understood that he had to go and break
that law and said salt is part of what
anybody needs to live and I'm breaking
the law on the basis of that truth and
that brought down the British Raj so I
think there's a need for the force of
truth that's how I would see things
thank you maybe will you ask your
question
hi thanks Michael for being here um
something that kind of stood up to me in
your introduction was this talk about
having like a brush with that like being
pushed past what you would be willing to
go through yourself if you were just
having to choose it in that moment and I
was wondering how you see like altered
states of consciousness as being
connected to initiation rights and other
transformative events like that great
question thank you so if I was going to
study initiation and all alternate
states of reality I would go
specifically to shamanic initiation and
well you could also go to Vision Quest
Vision Quest is pretty easy place to go
because they're still being done the
United States that's kind of a revival
and and the basic idea is you separate
from everybody and you go and sit in the
circle that you've made on some Ridge
somewhere no food maybe a little bit of
water nothing else exposed to nature but
all the ancient people saw nature as
spirit with the green garment on and so
you're really being exposed to the
alternatives alternative spirit of
nature and and then the idea is nature
spirit whatever you want to call it is
going to bring you something that's
going to turn out to be a totem animal
kind of way of understanding your psyche
or some other experience that alters and
and breaks through all common
expectation so that there is a personal
experience or a personal spiritual
experience it's not religious because
there's no church involved and there's
no doctrine it's actually the individual
opening now if you want to go back
through the tribal groups you're not
just opening to nature because nature is
part of the cosmic system or the cosmos
and so it's really the individual
opening to spirit to nature and to the
cosmos
that calls it causes a transcendence
natural transcendence and the person is
never the same so that would be one way
to go then you have shamanic initiation
which is you start the study of that in
Siberia the word shaman is a Siberian
word and this is interesting because
that happens when a person breaks down
so in the in the writer in the Vision
Quest you're you're going seeking the
vision in the shamanic thing it could be
you have a nervous breakdown and then
the people say oh well she's broken down
now so I guess maybe she wants to be a
shaman so you then go into a whole bunch
of wild experiences and the core idea is
that you die by dismemberment so you can
see how it could align with an emotional
breakdown or even a psychological
disorder because the imagery is that a
person is dismembered and then put back
together by the spirits and put back
together in a way that they're different
often they the imagery is that they'll
put certain crystals at the joints so
the person now doesn't just have bodily
joints sinews they also have crystals
there as if to say they have been remade
through mineral substance and then they
become the people who can when someone
gets lost which in the ancient world
would mean you lost your soul they have
the capacity to go find them because
they're now able to not just communicate
but transit through the other worlds and
so there's a whole field of study there
that is anthropological for the most
part but you can see the psychological
reverberations of it right away
and so if you want to relate it to
drug-taking for which people do for
vision and for transcending personality
and so on it fits into that shamanic
realm where there's going to be
something that
completely alters the person but it's
also useful for someone who has had a
breakdown they're separated by that
breakdown they're thrown into an
extremely mental condition how did they
come back having a diagnosis and getting
some drugs that doesn't bring them back
they're not in community but if they
were understood to be now open to other
unusual visions you bring them back as a
visionary and and suddenly they now
serve a function in this greater sense
of community ah so I hope that's helpful
with that rayo
where you ask your question yes thank
you Michael for being here I feel like
this kind of goes along with what you
just said I feel like I personally am
going through like a season of death
right now
kind of like dismantling and in my
experience many people are uncomfortable
or afraid of this idea of dying even
though to me it seems very essential for
self transcendence and then contributing
to communitas so do you have any advice
on how to be in right relationship with
the concept of death in order for us
individually and collectively to step
through this threshold to be reborn
really good question thank you so if
we're looking at it through the lens of
rites of passage and so the rites of
passage dynamic starts in youth and the
idea is you don't outgrow childhood
childhood has to die that's the old idea
and so there would be a brush with death
that could be like in the initiation of
girls and certain tribes in Africa the
actually girl
women are initiated individually to
begin with boys start out as a group and
then they try to find the individuality
the girls go when they have their first
menses what and and what is the menses
but blood going through the body and
taking out eggs that could have been
life that now go in the direction of
death it's so that the beginning of the
initiation would be the recognition that
the girl is now a woman and as a woman
she knows both life and death inside her
body and then and then they would so
then you would go out usually you're
taken away from the village it's all
happens out in nature and go into a
quiet dark Hut and be in darkness for a
while darkness equates to death
absence invisibility sometimes they
would be put in tight inside of a sacred
tree that was hollow as if going back
into the womb and that's the same place
that all the other women were when they
were becoming themselves and then so you
have this two sides to it one is death
childhoods over you'll never be that
child again and and then the other is
embryonic be like an embryo and so then
the young woman would be inside the tree
and this is an in demo tribe in what
used to be well it's the Congo now and
and then all the women come and feed her
as if she's an embryo and they give give
her actual food and they tell all the
stories of the feminine and all the
things that they know so she's getting
psychological and food and ideas and
mythological food and she would be in
there for a certain amount of time and
then she would come out of the tree as
if she was being born into the world as
a new person and the whole tribe had to
come and see the new person so so the
idea was you have to die to become a new
person and so one way to think about the
death is I make
distinction between little D deaths and
Big D death big D death is like the end
of the line the ropes run out you're
going on whether you're somewhere else
whether you like it or not little D
death you could call the death of the
ego something about the ego in the case
of youthful rites of passage just a
child
ego that has to die the rest of life we
have to have brushes with death that
diminish the ego the ego is a really
necessary thing but it is not the center
of a person it thinks it's the center of
the person but it's not there's a deeper
self and every time the ego can be
quieted the deeper self has a greater
chance to to express and to be present
and so the idea the the Irish have a
proverb death is the middle of a long
life or the mystical poet Rumi says die
before you die so our job is to keep
dying because in that we get reborn and
we become a bigger more enlivened
version of ourselves so good for you for
being in the season of death just as
long as you in touch with other people
and wrong will you ask a question thanks
Tyson hey Michael great to have you at
the stoah I actually saw you back in the
old days last year in person here in
Columbia Maryland and okay great just
got it in under the wire so it's good to
see you again I have another question
about individuation and the collective
and you already kind of addressed this
but maybe I can put a slightly different
tilt on it I definitely resonate with
your any one of your main themes of
we're living in an age or individuation
and people expressing their genius as
what's called for rather than a you know
a collective political movement or a
single idea or ideology or belief system
and when I preached that a lot of the
pushback I get from others is no no this
is an age of where the collective is
called for more than at any other time
and we're reeling
to lead with the collective and find
ways to come together with some
collective you know they may not use the
word ideology but they're kind of
pointing to that so I'm wondering how do
you talk about individuation in terms of
the collective and I know it's a tricky
thing is it's hard it's almost like a
circular thing because people expressing
their genius will be doing collective
things and forming a community oz as you
said so it's always her kind of hard to
talk about and in trying to make this
point so I'm wondering how you see those
those two I'm really familiar with that
conversation so my way of understanding
that is that the two are not opposed
that's a misunderstanding so I would
start with the idea no change at the
level of the individual soul no change
in the world so I'm saying it's really
complicated but
logically each soul is connected to the
soul of the world the old idea was anima
Mundi the world is alive and it has its
own soul and we each have our own soul
and there's a secret connection from the
individual soul to the soul of the world
so when there's an a greater awakening
of individual souls it generates the
energy and the ideas and images for
changing the collective and even
changing the world and so to me for
instance there cannot be a single idea
or an ideology to me ideology is what
you get when you've lost your
imagination that's what I think ideology
is not a high level of awareness as far
as I'm concerned so there's no ideology
there's no new political party there's
no single thing now the problems are too
big too complicated to historically
driven that it has to become a very
complex response and so then the way and
I grew up in the 60s and was part of the
collective revolution where we thought
politics could do a lot and it really
didn't come all the way through and the
same issues that were there then are
back now with a vengeance and politics
is less abled now in certain ways so not
that people shouldn't be political and
vote for the right folks and do all that
stuff but something else was trying to
happen and it has to happen from the
unique souls of people and then that
movement into the world from that inner
uniqueness is what changes the world and
so for instance
the United States we have some people in
high positions of authority in states
and in the federal government that shift
should not be there they don't have the
awakened sense of humanity they don't in
some cases have any empathy some of them
lack sympathy and so therefore they
cannot act in the interest of the
collective they just can't so what that
tells me is that some people are going
to have to wake up and become more
conscious of their own capacity to be a
leader in the collective political sense
that would be part of the individual
awakening as well in other words Martin
Luther King who is a very distinct
individual keeps awakening in the course
of his his political career but also his
earlier religious career he keeps
awakening to greater and greater things
until he has the dream of the next world
which at least he can pronounce and in
pronouncing and he even says I may not
get there that's the sign of the leader
understanding the process and so it
seems to me that when individuals awaken
some of them will be natural leaders
they will have the capacity and the aim
and the inclination and they just then
have to have the heart break open so
that have they have enough heartfelt
sense to use the talents and the skills
in a way that benefit everyone else so I
think the dichotomy between the the
fascination with a an ideology or
political movement and the uniqueness of
the individual and souls of false
dichotomy I think when enough people
awaken that will include the awakening
of natural leaders and and and then
people with in India they called it the
Dhamma actually the interesting old idea
was as spod Dhamma and it meant the
individual Dhamma awakening to the way I
am intended to serve the world and so
what would really change politics that
people and it doesn't matter their
background or their orientation or
anything it matters their genius if
people had
who had a genius for leading were in
positions of power that would make
communitas more possible so that's my
sense of it
Natalia will you ask your question thank
you I might also great to be here I
really admire your work
I'm wondering if you could talk about
the role of lineage and tradition in
this moment and in the process of
initiation so in some of these examples
of the liminal rituals you give with the
shamans and the denver tribe there
obviously have this community practice
of how to help people through these
liminal stages but obviously today
there's both too many traditions and
people are very fractured from them so
I'm wondering to what extent is it
important to have to be initiated
through a master or lineage and also
kind of what happens to lineages and
traditions more broadly in a time of
kind of a collective liminal collapse
and transformation really good questions
I don't know if I have a really good
answer
so start with an anecdote so once I was
in a car we were driving three and a
half four hours from the airport to a
remote camp we were going to have this
really radical conference and in the car
was an African medicine man with lineage
from the tribe a Buddhist teacher and
practitioner with absolute lineage way
back in he was an American but had
really been trained and initiated in
India a radical activist poet with
Native American and Latino background
and a Zen monk who was a lineage lineage
carrot Karia in Japan and myself and it
was the Buddhist leader who said how
about we have three and a half hours how
about we each talk about our lineage of
course he was quite comfortable with
that because he had a distinct lineage
which he gave the the description of how
he went got initiated and so on then the
african tribesmen talked about his
initiation and and how that connected to
the ancestors and how the ancestors
connected to the spirits of nature and
then the Zen master gave his description
of receiving the cloth of the lineage
which had been passed down for hundreds
and hundreds of years and then the
Latino poet activists and I looked at
each other and said what do we say and
so he good friend of mine Louise
Rodriguez he talked about his lineage in
both poetry and in politics in in in
activist politics but also then his
lineage by virtue of having both Latino
blood and his mother was from the the
Tara Mara a tribe in southern Mexico so
he had native tradition and and Mexican
Latino type tradition and so that's
where he went and then I I was really
happy to be last because I was trying to
figure out what's my lineage and so
where I went to I started naming William
Blake or William Butler Yeats and then
and back to the old Irish on Aki's who
were the seer storytellers and saying
none of these people do I actually know
but they are my lineage because I had to
build my lineage because I wasn't part
of any tradition per se and so in a way
that's those are the options you know
you can go the route of one of the
religious or spiritual practices and
then you can develop lineage that way or
be pulled into lineage through rituals
which was the case with this design
master
you could be born in a tribe somewhere
and then you'll get lineage or if you're
you know like I call it the outsider
you're outside the current culture
you're outside the traditional culture
you you then have to find your lineage
by virtue of imagination and by virtual
understanding the NE the inner lines of
the self to find lineage and so in my
sense lineage is it really a large thing
I don't know exactly what happens inside
the lineage groups now and how they deal
with all this stuff some of the
traditions have in the lineage practices
they have a like a wild card like in the
Zen tradition it was Iike you is called
the the criminal monk he's part of the
tradition but he did all his meditating
in the tavern and so but he's included
so they have like a wild card for how
you deal with unexpected periods of time
but the other thing I've been working on
is the outsider and so it starts in in
India which with what some people call
the outcasts but originally they were
called the outsiders and so the idea I
did there is if new ideas if new
imaginations are coming into a culture
they can't come in through the people
who see themselves and feel themselves
to be in the culture status quo as it is
they come in through the outsiders and
so I think there's a way to reimagine
being an outsider in the culture as
being a point of transmission for
knowledge trying to enter the world and
as being a messenger so maybe that's
helpful so that's what I'm working on
now is outsiders because we have less
structural lineal linear lineage
processes now in modern cultures so
anyway I hope that helps
thank you this brings up a question that
has been really alive for me and some of
my conversations recently and that is on
the cultural appropriation versus what
is cultural appreciation and I'm curious
in Europe like in your experience with
different cultures in my community
there's a lot of desire to participate
more fully in some of these rich
cultures to learn from the way that they
connect with the arts or with the land
and there's also like a sensitivity of
like Oh am i doing it wrong or like is
this this this isn't my I shouldn't
there's kind of this some sensitivity
around this whatever you might call that
that um this cultural appropriation
people cracking down on that so I'm
curious if you have any perspectives or
wisdom thoughts you might share on that
it's an important question is it's a
serious issue so the first thing that I
see if someone is saying we don't want
you messing with our traditions then
that that has to be respected and and
maybe there are meeting places like I
have a friend who wound up in a
traditional Buddhist temple but he sat
outside in the rain and the cold and and
the heat of the Sun for days before he
got invited in so sometimes you just
have to be nearby and be respectful and
then the door opens but on the other
hand there are traditional groups that
want to give you what they have most of
West Africa is that way the tradition is
in West Africa is whatever we have was
given to us by spirit we'll give it to
you as well so my first drum teacher was
that way you know someone actually tried
to try to take a drum away from me when
I was drumming in this event and I
instinctively held on to it and then I
went back to the teacher and said well
these people thought that
I was a white person playing African
music and they would try to take the
drum away and he said did you give it to
him I said no goes oh you're right
he said no one owns drumming it was
giving to me I gave it to you if you
want to give it away go ahead if you
don't then you know stay on the horse of
the drum so there's one idea and I don't
know I mean it's a big thing to study
and a person has to be respectful and
aware in the storytelling tradition the
storytellers certain kinds of
storytellers went between the tribes
went all around they had passage and
sometimes they wore a cloak of several
colors or they had something a feather
that indicated that they were moving
between the lineages and the tribes
because there needs to be communication
and cross pollenization also but here's
an anecdote I was doing a workshop and
up in the northwest where I live but
north of where I am and and into the
back of the room during the workshop
came a number of native people from
Lummi Nation and I've worked at Lummi
Nation I work with their young people
work with their elders and so they visit
if I'm around and it was right after
they got in that I had everybody had
been singing a chant from Africa and
then someone got up and asked are we
doing cultural appropriation by singing
someone else's song and I said well
actually I have permission to share that
song from the tribe tribal members I
said but we have some people from Lummi
Nation here so maybe we should ask them
are we doing some kind of cultural
appropriation and they got together and
had a talk and then afterwards and I was
waiting curiously maybe even uneasily to
find out they they might say cut it out
Michael you you're doing too much of
this or something but then the one of
the aunties they call him auntie she's
an elder she stood up and she said well
we discussed it
and we don't mind cultural appropriation
we don't what we mind is cultural
misappropriation it was a great
distinction and she said we know that
certain people are using traditions to
benefit the modern situation to open
people's hearts and minds
and so we judge by what the result is
not by what the premise is and so we
come here because we know what's going
to happen here and and then they offer
the song themselves in their native
language so so I think the distinction
between appropriation and
misappropriation is good and I think the
distinction between do people want to do
they want to share or is it something
they're preserving
those are some thoughts thank you that's
helpful
well that brings us now through the hour
thank you Michael for being here thank
you everyone for the really rich
questions Michael before we finished is
there anything that you would like to
leave us with yeah just to say Thank You
Tyson thank you for everybody for really
good questions good thoughts this is an
amazing time to be alive it can be
discouraging and disheartening but it's
really I think the transition to a
greater imagination and a different
world view view that's more inclusive of
everybody and lately this has been on my
mind this is one of my lineage people
William Blake who had this statement
that I carry around and I notice I'm
thinking about it a lot he said every
day has a moment of eternity waiting for
you in other words no matter how bad it
gets there's gonna be a moment where the
eternity the eternal was trying to reach
us and so part of what a practice is
about a practice helps me helps you
align with that moment of eternity more
often so in the midst of all the chaos
and all the discouraging things wishing
everybody moments of eternity
thank you well everybody if you would
like to experience more of Michaels work
you can visit the website here mosaic
voices org and they'll drop one more
link for you the store is operating on a
gift economy and if you wish to give a
gift to the stoy you can do so here and
thank you Michael for being here I'm
going to facilitate a 30-minute
sense-making practice now for anyone who
wishes to stick around if you've got to
go then that's alright
otherwise I look forward to continuing
this conversation with you so I'll give
it a minute for anyone who has to leave
to leave and do you want to get up and
get a glass of water or anything like
that
you can do so now thank you so much
Michael thanks Tyson thank you everybody
good luck be healthy be safe